（焦点影业）
（安培林娱乐）
出品公司
焦点影业
制作公司
赫拉影业
尼尔街制作公司
安培林娱乐
联合制作
暗影之书
哈姆奈特
（因为“哈姆奈特”与“哈姆雷特”事实上是同一名字）
（在16世纪末至17世纪初的斯特拉特福档案中可以互换使用）
（——《论哈姆奈特之死与〈哈姆雷特〉的渊源》）
【译注: 出自著名学者斯蒂芬·格林布拉特】
原创译制
蒙太奇字幕组
There you go.
你来了
There. You were hungry.
吃吧 你是饿坏了吧
That's it.
乖孩子
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
【译注: 正在朗读《农事诗》第三卷】
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
【《农事诗》: 维吉尔(古罗马诗人)农业诗篇 论耕作与农事纷争】
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径...
（拉丁语）...终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
（拉丁语）吾必另辟一径
（拉丁语）自当拔尘于世
（拉丁语）终有一日名扬四海
Repeat.
继续念
Good day, sir.
你好
Good day to you.
姑娘好
What brings you to Hewlands?
你来休兰农场来做什么？
I'm tutoring the boys here.
来这里教孩子
The Latin tutor.
教拉丁的先生啊
I've heard of you.
我听说过你
What brought you into the garden?
那你来这园里干什么？
Uh...
呃...
It's just a question, master tutor.
我就随便问问 教书先生
Yes, I, uh...
嗯 我 那个...
I suppose the air was fresh out here, and...
就是出来透透气 而且...
uh, I saw you with your bird.
呃 我看到你带着只鸟
- It's a hawk. - Ah.
- 那是只鹰 - 哦
May I?
能上前看看吗？
Don't get too close.
别凑太近
He doesn't know you.
他没见过你
Oh.
哦
Hello, boy.
你好 小家伙
Ah.
啊 哈哈哈
He likes you.
他喜欢你
What is your name?
你叫什么名字？
I shan't tell you.
别打听
You shall.
就打听
I shan't.
我不说
- You shall. - I won't.
- 你会说的 - 我不会
You'll tell me when we kiss.
等我亲你时你就会说了
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Agnes.
安妮丝
My name is Agnes.
我叫安妮丝
Where are you from?
你家哪儿的？
Have I said something?
我说错话了吗？
- Huh? - No.
- 啊？ - 没有
- You don't know who I am. - Wait, I wish to see...
- 你不知道我是谁 - 等下 我能去你...
You can't see me again.
你别再来找我了
Oh.
哦
Where have you been?
你去哪儿了？
I was in the field helping Bartholomew.
我下地帮巴塞洛缪
A newborn lamb is unwell.
小羊崽病了
Well, I... I went to the field.
好 我也去地里了
I did not see you there.
可没见你啊
Well, I was there. Tell her, Bartholomew.
我确实在那儿 巴塞洛缪哥 你给她说说
She was there.
她确实在那里
Have you seen the new Latin tutor?
你见过新来的拉丁先生吗？
The glover's son.
就是皮匠的儿子
The boys said he just ran out, never returned.
孩子们说他上着上着课跑掉了 就再没回来
He was supposed to give them lessons
他是来教书还债的
to pay off his father's debts.
还他父亲的债
I haven't seen him.
我没见过他
Well, should've known better.
算了 早该料到
Like father, like son.
父子都一个德行
You know, I do believe you are the prettiest girls in the parish.
你们俩可是咱们这教区最美的姑娘
- We are. - One day,
- 是的 - 将来...
I shall have my wits about me
会有许多人上门提亲
for all the suitors that will come for you.
我亲自把关 准把你们嫁个好人家
Agnes is the eldest. She'll marry first.
安妮丝是大姐 还轮不到我们
She will not if she keeps running off to the forest
她成天往树林里跑 像个流浪女
like a gypsy.
谁会娶她？
- When they said... - Where have you been?
- 他们说... - 你去哪儿了?
We were expecting you hours ago.
我们都等你好几个钟头了
- I was... - Well?
- 我在... - 说啊
I was working.
我在忙事儿
Sit.
坐下
快坐下吧
Your supper's near cold.
饭菜都凉了
- Uh, boys, boys! - Hey.
- 别闹 别闹 - 别抢
- Stop. - There's enough for all.
- 住手 - 大家都有份 别抢
How go the lessons at Hewlands?
休兰农场那边教得怎么样？
Those boys are no scholars.
那些孩子不是读书的料
- I wonder at the notion of all that learning. - Hmm.
- 我就纳闷 他们读书有啥用 - 嗯
Latin for boys who will be naught but sheep farmers.
注定务农的孩子学拉丁文？
- It is the putting on of airs. - No, no, no!
- 用来装模做样吗？ - 不 不 不
- That will do! - All right, Gilbert.
- 够了 - 都给你 吉尔伯特
You heard your mother. There's enough for all.
听你娘的 都有份 别争
You speak ill of the boys at Hewlands.
你说休兰那帮孩子不好
"They're no scholars."
“不是读书的料”
But I tell you something,
可我跟你说 他们将来...
they'll ever be more of a man than you are.
比你更像个男子汉
They are put to honest work, unlike you.
人家将来有正经活 你没有
Useless, tradeless, your fancy airs.
你没出息 没手艺 只会装模做样
All that education,
读那么多书
not an ounce of sense.
一点用都没有
I'm tutoring those boys to pay
我这没出息的去教书
your debts to that family, am I not?
不就是替你还那户人家的债吗？
Your immeasurable amount of debt,
你欠休兰家那么多债
Didn't I help you... Stop!
要不是我... 住手
What of the rest of the family at Hewlands?
休兰那边其他人
Have you met them?
你都见过吗？
The mother only.
只见过那户的母亲
- Not the eldest daughter? - No.
- 那大女儿没见到吗？ - 没有
It is said the girl is the child of a forest witch.
大家都说 那姑娘是森林巫婆的后代
I've seen her, wandering the back roads alone
我就见过 她独自走在山路上
with a hawk on her arm.
臂上还有只鹰
A hawk at Hewlands?
休兰那儿还有鹰？
Yes.
是的
They say she takes him to the forest with her unaccompanied.
传言说她每次进林都是一个人带着那只鹰
Yeah, but are you certain, Eliza?
你确定吗 伊莱莎？
The eldest daughter keeps a hawk, not a servant girl?
那拿着鹰的是长女 不是仆人？
Yes. Yeah.
不是仆人 我确定
Agnes.
安妮丝
Hello.
你好
What are you doing here?
你跑来这儿干什么？
Brought you this.
送你个东西
What is it?
这是什么？
It's, uh...
这是...
it's a new glove for your bird.
给你那只鸟的新手套
I have a glove.
我有手套了
Agnes.
安妮丝
Agnes, wait.
安妮丝 别跑
I know who you are.
我认出你了
Who am I?
那好 我是谁？
Well, I... I don't know you, but I've heard things...
好吧 不算了解你 只是听到些传言...
I'm the daughter of a forest witch?
说我是森林巫婆的女儿？
Yes. People say that, but I-I don't care...
是啊 村里这么说 但我 我不在意...
I am my mother's daughter.
我可是我母亲的女儿
I've learnt many things from her.
从她那儿学的本事多着呢
What are you looking at?
你瞎看什么？
- You. - Why?
- 看你 - 为什么？
- I... - I thought you were a man of words, master tutor.
- 因... - 你这教书的 不该能言善辩吗？
Yes.
是的
- Are you not? - Jus...
- 还难住你了？ - 只是...
Speaking with people is sometimes difficult for me.
我有时很难直接跟人说话
Well, tell me a story, then.
好 那就讲个故事吧
- A story? - Yes.
- 讲故事？ - 对
What story would you like?
你想听什么故事？
Something that moves you.
起码能打动你自己的故事
All right.
好吧
Do you know the story of Orpheus and Eurydice?
你知道俄耳甫斯和欧律狄刻的故事吗？
【译注: 古希腊神话】
Orpheus is...
俄耳甫斯这个男人
a man of music.
有着天赋异禀的音乐才能
He has this exquisite voice.
他还有着天籁般的嗓音
His playing of the kithara, which is a...
他弹那种七弦里拉 是...
is-is a harp-like lyre,
是类似竖琴的乐器
is so divine,
声音美得妙不可言
birds, the...
连天上的鸟儿 地...
the beasts, e-even the stones and the trees,
地上的走兽 甚 甚至石头和树
they all moved to the rhythm of his music.
都能被他的音乐打动随之起舞
Now, Orpheus falls in love with this beautiful nymph, Eurydice.
后来 俄耳甫斯爱上了一位美丽的山林少女 叫欧律狄刻
Soon after their marriage,
和山林少女刚结完婚
Eurydice's bitten by a viper
她就被毒蛇咬了
and poison courses through her body,
毒素在她体内迅速扩散
and she's killed.
她就此身亡
And Orpheus, filled with grief,
俄耳甫斯悲痛欲绝
journeys to the underworld to take her back.
下到冥府想要将她带回
He charms this three-headed dog, Cerberus.
他用琴声迷住了守门的三头犬 刻耳柏洛斯
He beguiles Hades until finally...
甚至感动了冥王哈得斯 最终...
...he's allowed to take his love back with him
冥王同意了
to the world of the living but...
允许把这名女子带回人间 但...
...under one condition.
但有一个条件
What is it?
什么条件？
She must follow behind him,
这名女子必须跟在他身后
and he must not turn around to look at her.
而他绝对不能回头看
Now, as they begin their ascent,
现在 他们开始往人间走
Orpheus can't hear her footsteps, so he listens...
俄耳甫斯却听不见他妻子的脚步声 于是他听啊...
...and listens and listens and listens.
听啊 听啊 一直听
But all he can hear is the sound of his heartbeat.
他只听得见自己的心跳
And the rest is silence.
余下的只有沉寂
And as he approaches the gates of the underworld...
当他快到冥门出口时
...he can't contain himself any longer.
他忍不住了
He turns around to look at her, and she is...
他回头去看妻子 然后妻子...
...trapped in the underworld forever.
永远被困在冥府里了
Hmm.
嗯
That was a good story.
这是个好故事
Did you like it?
你喜欢吗？
Remember, mugwort, what you brought to pass,
艾草者 古之名药也
【《九草咒》: 古英语药咒 列九种草药以驱毒治疫】
what you readied at Regenmeld.
世人皆知其德 传颂至今
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You defy three, you defy 30,
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
And you, waybread, plant mother,
车前草者 草之母也
you're open to the east yet mighty within.
根植东方 性禀刚毅
Carts creeped over you, women rode over you.
遭车碾而不折 遇众踏而复起
You withstood it all, and you pushed back.
刚柔相济 疗人间之疾苦
Is it true that you know everything about a person
你真的能靠摸一个人的手
by touching them here?
看透一切吗？
Not everything.
并非全部
When you touched me here, what did you see?
你摸我时你看到了什么？
I saw a landscape.
我看见了一幅画面
- You saw a landscape? - Mm-hmm.
- 一幅画？ - 嗯
Spaces, caves, cliff tops,
空洞 黑洞 裂口
tunnels and oceans,
暗道和深海
this deep, dark, black void,
深不见底 一片漆黑的虚空
undiscovered countries.
未知的国度
（拉丁语）天道有常 宿命有律
【译注: 正在朗读《农事诗》第一卷】
（拉丁语）万物难逃衰落之数 消亡乃其必然
（拉丁语）天道有常 宿命有律
She speaks...
她说话了...
She speaks, she speaks.
她说话了 她说话了
But, soft,
且慢
what light through yonder window breaks?
那窗户透出来的是什么光？
It is the east, and Juliet is the sun...
那是东方 朱丽叶就是太阳...
...and kill...
赶走那....
...the envious moon.
嫉妒的月亮
【译注: 正在创作《罗密欧与朱丽叶》第二幕第二场】
Hello.
你好
I wish to be handfasted to you.
我要和你成亲
No, I... I must be handfasted to you.
不 我 我必须和你成亲
No one else will do.
非你不可
I-I will speak with your stepmother and your brother,
我会去跟你继母和你哥哥说
and of course they will not agree, but...
估计他们不会答应
I don't care because I have no talent for waiting.
不管行不行就这么定了 不能等了
I cannot abide waiting.
哪怕是私定终身
What about your parents?
那你父母怎么办？
Your parents will never agree.
他们绝不会答应的
Follow me.
跟我来
Wait. Wait. W-Wait.
等 等 等下
- No! - No!
- 跑不掉了 - 别
My glove.
我的手套
- This is my mother's glove. - Hmm.
- 是我母亲留给我的 - 哦
She came out of the woods...
她源于森林
...like her mother
就像她的母亲一样
and her mother before her.
像她母亲的母亲一样
The women in my family see things...
我家族女人能看到些...
...that others don't.
别人看不到的东西
Agnes.
安妮丝
Remember, mugwort,
艾草者 古之名药也
what you brought to pass, what you readied at Regenmeld.
世人皆知其德 传颂至今
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You defy three, you defy 30,
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
Bartholomew, it will heal.
巴塞洛缪 会好的
Will it make a scar?
会留疤吗？
It may. That's no bad thing.
可能会 但并非坏事
Listen.
听
Do you hear that?
听见了么？
You must pay attention to your dreams, Agnes.
留心你的梦 安妮丝
They will always guide you.
梦永远会指引你
- Good day. - Good day.
- 你们好 - 你也好
Yes.
好
Agnes, what's, uh...
安妮丝 你怎么在...
what's happened?
你怎么在这儿？
Her mother has banished her from their house.
她母亲把她逐出家门了
She's not my mother.
她不是我生母 而且...
The house belongs to my brother, Bartholomew.
我家那房子归我哥哥巴塞洛缪
I chose to leave.
我是自愿离开的
She's with child.
她有身孕了
Oh.
哦
Says it's yours.
还说孩子是你的
- Is it? Yours? - Uh...
- 真的吗？真是你的吗？ - 呃...
The child in her belly, did you put it there?
她肚子里的孩子 是你弄的吗？
I did.
是我
- We are handfasted, Mother. - We will never allow it!
- 我们已经私定了 娘 - 休想
- There is no sin in it. - I'm afraid you will need
- 这有什么错啊 - 没我们的同意
- our consent, and we will... - There is no sin in it!
- 你成不了亲的 - 这有什么错啊
- ...we will never give it, ever! - All right!
- 我们决不允许这桩婚事 - 行 行
What?
啥？
- You've been bewitched. - No.
- 你被她蛊惑了 - 不是的
I'd rather you went to sea than marry this wench.
我宁愿你当水手送命 也别娶这个巫婆
Mary.
玛丽
There's no need for that.
不必这样
I have no doubt we can come to an arrangement.
既然他们两厢情愿 这事好解决
- John. - Hush, woman.
- 约翰 - 安静 女人
I am certain you are eager
你肯定想在教堂里
to see your sister before the altar.
看到你妹妹出嫁吧
I'm certain you'd rather not see your boy
我肯定想现在
dragged before the bawdy court.
控告你儿子奸淫
There's no need for that.
没必要闹成那样
They said they are handfasted.
他们都已经私定了
Only if I say so.
嫁不嫁由我说了算
But why marry a pasty-faced scholar? What use is he?
嫁给那白面书生到底有啥好处？他有什么用
He's got more inside of him than any man I've ever met.
他的内心比我见过的任何人都深邃
Everything will change.
人心是会变的
You. You will change.
你 你也不例外
I'm already changing.
我的心已经变了
It's too quiet in there.
里头太静了
In where?
哪儿里头？
That house.
他们家
What would our mother say to us if we were afraid or uncertain?
记得我们害怕迷茫时 娘怎么劝咱的吗？
To live with our hearts open.
我们要敞开心扉
To shut it not in the dark
别叫它躲在黑暗里
but to turn it to the sun.
而是转向太阳
He loves me for what I am, not what I ought to be.
他爱的是我本色 不图我变成谁
Then marry him you shall.
那就嫁给他吧
Thank you.
谢谢
Remember, mugwort...
艾草者 古之名药也
Say it with me. Say it with me.
来 说跟我一起说 一起说
What you brought to pass,
世人皆知其德
what you readied at Regenmeld.
传颂至今
You are called Una, the most ancient plant.
其名曰艾 为草之首
You defy three, you defy 30,
能驱三疾 能制三十疾
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
能解毒气 能散瘴疠
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
能降瘟疫 克之而胜
Look at me.
回头看我
Agnes.
安妮丝
Hey.
嘿
Look. Look at that. Look at the fire.
看 看那光 那是火
Mmm, what's that?
看看 那是什么啊
The doggy dragged something in.
是小狗叼进来的东西
There's something.
快看
Oh.
哦
Daddy's coming.
你爹回来了
Hello.
回来了
Stitches need to be smaller.
针脚要小一点
M-Much smaller.
再小 再小一点
Yes.
对
Hmm.
哼
Useless.
没出息
Okay, and now...
好 再小点
smaller.
再小点
- Where are you going? - I'm going.
- 你去哪儿？ - 我要出去
Get back to work.
回去干活
That was the last time you will ever hit me.
这是你最后一次打我
Do you understand?
明白吗？
- Do you understand?! - Yes.
- 明白吗？ - 明白
My love, you should come back to bed.
爱人 该睡觉了
What are you writing?
你在写什么？
Nothing of note.
不值一提
It's never nothing.
总有值得称道的地方
I don't know.
还没写好呢
Perhaps when it's finished, it will...
也许写完会好...
Perhaps when it's finished.
也许吧
Why don't you read me what you've written?
念给我听听吧
A-Agnes, it's not--
安妮丝 这还没...
It-It's not finished.
还没写好呢
It's not finished.
没写好
Stop it. You'll wake the baby.
别敲了 吵醒孩子了
It's okay.
好了
No. It's okay.
不哭 不哭
I'm sorry.
对不起
I've had too much, uh...
我喝多了
Agnes, I've had too much to drink.
安妮丝 我喝多了
I've had...
我喝...
I've had too much to drink.
我喝的太多了
Hey.
嘿
What is it?
有什么心事吗？
Give me your hand.
我给你的手看看
Pl-Pl-Please, please, please, please,
别 别 别 别 别
please, please, please, please.
别 别 求你了 别
- What are you afraid I will see? - Please stop.
- 你怕我看见什么吗？ - 求你了 别
That I am a violent and dangerous man.
我怕我将来会伤害你
No, you are none of those things.
不会 你不是那样的人
- How do you know? - You're a good man. You're a...
- 你怎么能肯定？ - 你是个好人 你是个...
You are a good man.
你是个好人
You're a good man.
Is it that you wish that we never wed?
难道是后悔跟我结婚了吗？
How could you say such a thing?
怎么能说出这种话？
你怎么能说出这种话？
You and Susanna are all that I live for.
我活着就是为了你和苏珊娜
All that I live for.
我活着就是为了你们
- What is it, then? - This...
- 那到底怎么回事？ - 是...
- Here. Look at me. - Just stop!
- 来 把手给我 - 停下
Stop, stop. Please, please, please, please, please, please.
停 停 求你停下 停 停 停
Look at me.
看着我
Listen. Listen. Listen.
听着 听着 听我说
I'm lost.
我迷失了
I've lost my...
我找不...
I've lost my way.
我找不到方向了
I just need to-- uh, Agnes, I just need to work.
我需要 我需要静下心好好写作 安妮丝
He's not sleeping.
他都睡不着觉
- Has he ever lost his temper with you? - No.
- 他对你发火了吗？ - 没有
- If he raises a hand... - No, he has never. He's never.
- 要是他对你动手.... - 没有 他从没那样 从没那样
He's angry with himself.
他只是为自己懊恼
He's sick with himself.
心里难受得要命
He's a good man.
他是个好人
He's a good husband, he's a good father,
是个好丈夫 也是个好父亲
but he n-needs more.
但他还需要更多
What could he possibly need other than his family and you?
他已经有了家和你 还能需要什么？
- He has you. - He needs to go to London.
- 他已经有了你 - 他需要去伦敦
- London? - Yeah.
- 伦敦？ - 是的
Why London?
为啥去伦敦？
Because London is where the whole world gathers.
因为伦敦汇聚天下
Perhaps he could extend his father's business there.
说不定能把他爹的手艺带去发扬光大
- Oh, you're being hasty again. - Who knows what he may be...
- 哎 你又冲动了 - 谁知道他将来会怎样
I'm not being hasty. He needs more.
我不是冲动 他需要更多
- Well, he needs proper work. - He's not of this world.
- 他只是太闲了 - 他不该呆这小地方
The man needs proper work.
给他找个活儿忙起来
- What's in this little town? - He can't just run away.
- 这小地方能有什么出路？ -  他不能就这么跑掉
This little life? This little thing, it'll...
这小日子 这小地方
...crush him.
会逼疯他的
He needs distance from his father.
他得离他爹远点
And you would go with him to London?
你跟他一起去伦敦吗？
No, I'll wait until he's settled.
不 等他安顿好再说
There'll be more of us soon.
马上家里就会多一口人
- Another child? - Yes.
- 又怀上了？ - 是的
By summer's end.
夏末时候生
Then now is not the time to send him away.
那现在更不能把他送走了
I'll lose him.
那我会失去他的
I'm already losing him.
我已经在失去他了
You'll lose him if you send him away.
要是送他走 就彻底失去他了
No, I know, I know that our love will keep us steady.
不 不会的 我肯定我俩的爱能维系得住
Please. Will you speak to his father?
求你了 替我跟他爹说说吧
He'll listen to you if you suggest him going to London.
要是你跟他提去伦敦的事 他会听你的
Please.
求你了
I should find lodgings.
我得找个住处
Be near the river, close to the tanneries.
最好靠河的 离河边皮革场近点
But I'm told that the currents in the river are dangerous
我听说那河水很急
and that you must engage an experienced boatman
过河要请有经验的船夫
every time you cross, and I'll be certain to do that every time,
每次过河我都照办
I promise.
我保证
And I will think of you and Susanna
我会时时刻刻
with every passing moment.
挂念你和苏珊娜的
And I will find us lodgings in London,
我会给咱们找个好住处
and we shall all be together again.
到时候在伦敦团聚
Do you still not know if it's a boy or a girl?
你还没预见出是男孩还是女孩吗？
No.
没有
Don't know why.
我也说不清为什么
Have you not said that you would always have two children?
你不是说过会有两个孩子陪你到最后吗？
Yes.
是的
Two children at my deathbed.
临终前会有两个孩子在身边
Well, then, here is the second.
第二个能陪你到最后的人来了
- We won't say goodbye. - No.
- 咱们就别道别了 - 好
You get-- Go.
别磨蹭了 快走吧
- You going somewhere? - No, I'm just...
- 你要出门吗？ - 不是 我只是...
Yes, I'm going to the lake...
对 我要去湖边走走...
You're not going to the forest.
你不许进森林
- I must. - No, you must not. Gilbert!
- 我非去不可 - 不 你不许去 吉尔伯特快来
You... you have to let me go there.
你 你得让我去那里
- Let me go there! - Listen Agnes.
- 你必须让我走 - 听我说 安妮丝
- You must let me go! - The river has burst its banks!
- 你得放我去 - 河堤已经决口了
- Let me! - There is no way...
- 让我去 - 外面很危险
- There's no way to get to the forest. - Let me! No!
- 根本没路去森林那边 - 放我走 不要
- We have everything ready for you. - My baby!
- 我们都为你准备好了 - 我孩子
No, my-my baby.
不 我 我孩子
I can't.
我不行
It isn't coming out.
生不出来
I will not have my baby in this house.
我没法在这屋里生孩子
Not in this house.
没法在这屋
No.
没法
The river.
河水
- Hush, hush, hush, hush. Hush. - No, no, no, no.
- 使劲儿 使劲儿 使劲儿 - 不 不 不
He spoke about the river.
他说要住河边
The river is dangerous. He may be swept downstream!
河很危险 他可能会被冲走
Agnes. Agnes.
安妮丝 安妮丝
Agnes. Agnes, all is well with him.
安妮丝 安妮丝 他一切安好
Do you not recall his last letter?
你难道忘了他最近的信吗？
Stop the screaming.
别叫了
You'll wake the whole town.
会把整村人都吵醒的
He sound...
他语气...
He sounded different.
他语气不对
No, he had good news for us.
不 他带来的是好消息
- The theater. - Theater.
- 剧院 - 剧院
He has a contract with the players
他和剧团定下来了
- to make gloves for the theater. - the theater
- 做剧院用的手套 - 剧院
Agnes, hush now.
安妮丝 使劲儿
Hush. Hush. Hush.
使劲儿 使劲儿 使劲儿
Bear down. Bear down.
用力 用力
Ah! Ooh!
来了 来了
- There we go. - It's a boy.
- 出来了 - 是个男孩
There we go.
真好
Good boy. Good boy.
乖孩子 乖孩子
It's a boy.
是个男孩
My boy.
我的儿子
Thank you.
谢谢你
What is it? What's happening?
怎么回事？怎么了？
She's starting again.
她又要生了
- You're having twins, my girl. - Come on, Eliza.
- 姑娘啊 你怀的是双胞胎 - 来 伊莱莎
Here. Quickly.
快 抱着他
Take him.
抱好
No, no, no.
不 不 不
Two standing at my deathbed.
我临终前会有两个孩子在身边
I always believed that it would be...
我一直以为...
that they would be my children.
一直以为是长大的孩子
And now...
现在我...
now I see it will be you.
我明白了 原来就是你们俩
We need to get you to the stool.
得把你扶到产凳上
It's coming. It's here.
快生了 要生了
- No. - Come on. Come on up. Up, up.
- 不要 - 来 来 起来 起来
Please. I can't... I...
别 我 我不行
I can't.
我不行
- Go. - I should never have...
- 来 - 我不该...
I can't...
我不行了...
I can't make it.
我挺不过去了
I got it wrong. I got it wrong.
我弄错了 我弄错了
I got it...
我弄错...
He... He's not here.
他 他不在
He's... He's not here.
他 他不在这里
Agnes, you can...
安妮丝 你能行的
and you must.
你必须行
I cannot.
我不行
Agnes.
安妮丝
You can...
你能行的
and you will.
你会挺过去的
Your husband was born here in this room.
你丈夫就在这间屋里出生
He took his first breath there by the window.
他就在那窗边 第一次呼吸
Please.
求求你
Please let this child live.
求求你 保住孩子
Let this child live. Please.
一定保孩子 一定
Will you let him...
让他...
Let him come back and be with his child.
让他回到家后能有孩子陪他
Please.
求你了
Let him think kindly of me always.
让他对我留个好念想
Remember me.
记着我
Mama.
娘
Mum?
娘？
Just too weak.
她没抗住
She was in too much pain.
她承受了很大的痛苦
I mean, poor woman.
太可怜了
She just got weaker and weaker.
越来越痛 她承受不住了
I mean, that's just the way of it sometimes.
有时候命就是这样
She-she must have known the end was nigh.
她 她大概早就知道这一刻了
Best not speak of her to the children.
最好别跟孩子提起她了
Safer with a different mother.
再娶一个吧
So young.
孩子都还小
They may not remember her.
兴许能忘掉
- Mum! - Agnes. Agnes.
- 娘啊 - 安妮丝 安妮丝
- Mama, no! - No, no. Agnes.
- 娘啊 不 - 不 不 安妮丝
Child. Child.
孩子 孩子
- Mummy, no! - No, no, no. Ch-Ch-Ch-- No.
- 娘 不要 - 不 不 孩子 孩子 不行
- No! - No.
- 放开我 - 不行
- No, let me see her! - No, no!
- 不 让我见娘 - 不 不
- Let me see her! - No!
- 我要见娘 - 不
No, Mama!
不 娘
- Agnes. - No!
- 安妮丝 - 不
Mum. I want, I want my mum.
娘 我要我娘 我要我娘
I want my mum...
我要我娘啊...
Oh! Here we go! It's a girl!
来了 是个女孩
It's a girl. She's...
是个女孩 她...
- It's... Wait. - What?
- 等等... - 怎么了？
Come on. Come on.
快点 快点
Why is she not crying?
她怎么不哭？
She lives not.
她没活过来
Let me have her.
让我抱抱
You should not look upon her. It's bad luck.
不行 这不吉利
Give her to me.
把她给我
I'll make sure it gets a decent burial.
我会把她安葬妥当的
Give me my child!
把我孩子给我
【双胞胎: 当时双胞胎被视为怪异现象和不祥征兆】
My child.
我的孩子啊
Agnes, you have a baby boy.
安妮丝 你有个儿子
Let me bring him to you, and you may feed him.
我把他抱来 你可以喂他
The girl has gone to heaven.
女孩已经去了天国
She's not gone to heaven.
她不会去天国的
I made a vow the night my mother died.
我母亲去世那晚我发过誓
I will go to your church, but I shan't say a word there.
我会去你们的教堂 但别指望我开口说什么
【译注: 当时无宗教自由 故以含蓄方式表达不信教】
Yes. Yes. Yes.
太好了 太好了 太好了
You will live.
你会活下去的
I will make sure nothing ever takes you away.
我会保护你到底 绝不放手
I actually couldn't find it.
我怎么都找不到
Hmm.
没有
Here.
找到了
Perfect.
太好了
I found my hat.
找到帽子了
Okay. Yes.
来 对
Okay, take that side. Take that side.
来 转过去 转过去
Yeah.
好
And put it around here.
然后系好
Perfect.
完美
- Ooh. Sorry. - Let me help you.
- 哎呀 - 我来吧
It's down my face.
挡到我脸了
- I'm Hamnet. - I'm Hamnet.
- 跟我学“我是哈姆奈特” - “我是哈姆奈特”
- I'm Judith. - I'm Judith.
- “我是珠迪丝” - “我是珠迪丝”
There will be no running in this house.
屋里不准跑
Conduct yourselves, please, as...
你们要举止端正 要像...
gentlewomen and gentlemen.
淑女与绅士
Where are you going?
你们要去哪儿？
Yeah. He's-he's coming. He's coming.
对 他来了 他来了
Hello.
回来了
你回来了
We all know they've swapped clothes.
一看就知道他俩对调了衣服
How long are we going to pretend we don't?
咱们什么时候揭穿？
We'll pretend for as long as they think they're the same.
只要他们继续演 咱们就不揭穿
Hi.
你好
Father, will you help me with the Greek passage
爹 能再教我下
from yesterday's lesson?
昨天那段希腊文吗？
Hamnet, I thought you'd already learnt it.
哈姆奈特 你不是会背了吗？
I didn't because I left my primer at school.
我忘了 因为把课本落学堂了
Well, Hamnet,
好吧 哈姆奈特
you need to take your studies seriously.
你要用心学
How do you expect to improve if you're not...
不努力怎么会进步...
（希腊语）吾不肯苟且而生 不甘平庸而逝
【译注: 正在朗读荷马《伊利亚特》第22卷】
（希腊语）愿成就丰功伟绩 令后世永传吾名
【《伊利亚特》: 荷马(古希腊诗人)史诗 论英雄 战争与命运】
You rascals.
你们这群小淘气
- Did we trick you? - Of course you did.
- 我们耍到你了吗？ - 当然了
You swapped places to hoodwink me again.
你们又互换来耍我
【译注: 当时女性普遍无法接受正规教育 现实中他妻女都不识字】
Susanna, come here.
苏珊娜 过来
Come here.
快过来
Now, do you remember the thing we were going to do for your mother?
你们还记得要给娘准备的那件事吗？
- Yeah. - You remember? You ready to do it?
- 嗯 - 都记得吗？准备好了吗？
- Yeah. - Okay. Go outside quickly.
- 嗯 - 好 快去 快去准备
Go, go, go, go, go.
快去 快去 快去
- Just step toward... - Wait.
- 朝前走 - 别急
One st-- Come to your right. Step.
再走 往右走 小心
Step. One more.
慢点 再迈一步
- What. - One more.
- 啥 - 再迈一步
When shall we three meet again?
咱们三个儿啥时候再聚？
In thunder, lightning or in rain?
等打雷 等闪电 还是等下雨？
When hurly-burly's done, when the battle's lost and won!
等到这场吵闹都停了 等到这一仗打出个输赢了
That will be ere at set of sun.
那就在太阳落山以前
- Where the place? - Upon the heath.
- 在什么地方？ - 就在荒原
There to meet with Agnes.
在那儿同安妮丝会面
I come, Graymalkin.
我来了 灰妖猫
Paddock calls.
蛤蟆叫
Anon!
马上到
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
美即是丑 丑即是美
Fair is foul and foul is fair. Fair is foul and foul is fair.
美即是丑 丑即是美 美即是丑 丑即是美
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
美即是丑 丑即是美
Hover through the...
穿入到...
【《麦克白》: 出自第一幕第一场 参考卞之琳译本】
Well done!
演得好
That was amazing!
真精彩
Dig it deep, and then you move all of it to the side,
挖深点 把土拨到一边
and then you put it down here.
然后把根放进去
Right? And then you get the soil around the sides,
明白吧 然后把土填回去
and then you pat it more.
用手把土拍平
And then you get bits like that.
然后手上就沾了土
And you rub it in your hands.
然后两手搓一搓
Whoa. And then back!
等下 向后退
Do this.
照我这样做
And when you're doing this, circle.
然后转圈 盯住对手
Yeah, like that.
对 就是这样
Ready?
准备好了吗？
Forward. And back.
前进 后撤
Now, parry, parry, parry.
现在 挡剑 挡剑 挡剑
Good. Again.
很好 再来
Now, after that one, I'm gonna do this,
接着 我出这招
and you get out of the way.
你要闪开
Ready? Circle off. Spin your sword.
准备好了吗？绕圈走 转动你的剑
No.
不对
Circle, spin your sword.
绕圈 把剑转起来
Now, come forward.
现在 向前迈
And go back.
再往后退
One, two three.
挡剑三次
Out of the way!
闪开
Very good. Again.
非常好 再来一次
Judith, what's this one called?
珠迪丝 闻闻这是什么？
- Thyme. Thyme. - Rosemary.
- 百里香 百里香 - 是迷迭香
-Thyme. - Thyme. Thyme.
- 是百里香 - 好吧 百里香 百里香
- I got it mixed up. - That's okay.
- 我记错了 - 没关系
This one...
这株是...
- Now, that's rosemary. - Yeah.
- 这是迷迭香 - 对
And what is rosemary for?
迷迭香有什么用处？
- Putting it in apples. - Apples.
- 放在苹果里一起炖 - 炖苹果
No. What is Rosemary's for?
不对 再闻闻
- Remembering. - Remembering.
- 记忆 - 纪念
Remembering.
对 记忆纪念
Now, you're to rub all this in your hands.
现在 搓一搓
You blow a little wish.
吹个小心愿进去
To wish him on his way.
许个愿 让他带走
Yeah? And it's your secret with him.
明白吗？这就是你和他的小秘密了
Did you see him?
看见了吗？
Did you not see him in the sky?
没看见他在天上吗？
All right, do it again.
好 再来一次
Make another wish.
再许个愿
Look. Right up there.
看 就在上面
Look, just there. Did you see him?
就在那里 看见了吗？
And he's got all your wishes tucked in his little heart.
他把你们所有的愿望都藏在他的小心窝里了
So any time that you want to remember him,
每当想念他的时候
you just have to go...
只要吹一下...
Where are you going?
你要去哪儿？
Huh? I'm gonna catch you!
我来抓你了
I'm gonna catch you!
Father?
爹？
Is all well?
没事吧？
Yes.
没事
Listen, I want you to stay away from your grandfather.
听着 别太靠近你爷爷
He'll not hit your sisters, but it's you that I worry for,
他不会打你姐妹 但我担心你
and I need to know that you'll be safe when I'm not here.
当我走了你要能保护好自己
You're going back to London again?
又要回伦敦了么？
Yes, tomorrow.
对 明天
Tomorrow?
明天就走？
It's all right.
没关系的
Will we go with you this time?
这次我们能跟你一起去吗？
No, not yet.
不行 还不行
Hey.
嘿
I'll miss you.
我会想念你的
But I have to go, you understand? I...
但我得走 你明白吗？我得...
I know.
我懂
I understand.
我明白
That's good.
那就好
'Cause I need you to look after your mother and your sisters.
你要替我照顾好你娘和你姐妹
Will you do that?
能做到吗？
Yes.
能
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
- 能做个男子汉吗？ - 能
Yes?
真的吗？
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
- 你勇敢吗？ - 是
Will you be brave?!
是男子汉吗？
- Huh?! - Yes! Yes, I'll be brave!
- 是吗？ - 是 是 我是男子汉
I'll be brave. I'll be brave.
我很勇敢 我是男子汉
I've looked at houses for us in London.
我已经在伦敦替咱们物色好房子了
-Autumn is coming. - Mm.
- 秋天就要来了 - 嗯
And the children will fall ill.
孩子们会生病的
Judith, she's still not strong enough.
珠迪丝还是太虚弱了
She often gets congestion in her chest.
她常常胸闷
And the air in London is...
伦敦那空气...
We can't.
去不了
But one day soon, we will.
但迟早有一天 我们会去的
We will come to London with you.
我们会跟你去伦敦的
No, you won't.
不会的
You'll never come.
你永远不会来的
You've waited for the heat of summer to pass...
夏天你嫌太热
...the dryness of autumn,
秋天干燥
the snow and the cold.
冬天太冷
You do not believe that Judith will ever survive London.
你压根儿不信珠迪丝能在伦敦活着
You'd do anything in your power to keep that child alive.
你会想尽一切办法保住那孩子
Isn't that what a mother is supposed to do?
做母亲的不就该这样吗？
Of course it is.
当然是
So...
所以...
...I've decided to look for land outside Stratford.
我决定就在这镇子附近给咱们找个家
That's where you should live with the children.
你和孩子们还在斯特拉特福镇这片生活
【斯特拉特福: 距离伦敦160公里 当时为羊毛 皮革等畜产品加工地】
- Thank you. - Mm-hmm.
- 谢谢你 - 嗯
Ooh!
来吧
Where is she? Ah!
快过来 啊
Hamnet. There he is.
哈姆奈特呢 你来了
Come here.
过来吧
I love you. I love you. I love you.
爱你 爱你 爱你
All right. Love you.
行了 来亲一下
- Come on. - Love you.
- 好了 - 亲一下
Love you.
亲一下
Oh.
哦
All right. Come here.
好吧 过来
- Remember what I told you, okay? - Okay.
- 还记得我告诉你的话吗？ - 记得
Good boy.
好孩子
- Bye. - Bye.
- 我要走了 - 再见
- 走了 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
- 真走了 - 再见
Hamnet?
怎么了 哈姆奈特？
Come on. Come here.
过来 到这儿来
Show me your hand.
把手给我
What? What do you see?
你 你看到什么了？
I see you.
我看到你...
Grown.
长大了
And very strong.
身强力壮
And I see you in London working with your father.
我还看到你在伦敦 和你父亲一起工作
- In the theater? - Yes.
- 在剧院吗？ - 对
At the playhouse.
在剧场
What will I be doing?
我会在那儿做什么？
What do you wish to do, Hamnet?
你想做什么呢？
I should be one of the players with a sword.
我想当个拿剑的演员
A sword?
拿剑的？
Yes.
对
And I shall clash it against the sword of the other player.
我想拿剑和其他演员交锋
Show me.
示范给我看看
There'll be a terrible fight,
会有场激烈的战斗
and everybody watching will be frightened out of their wits.
观众看得心惊胆战
And who will win?
那谁会赢呢？
I shall, of course.
自然是我
Of course you shall.
当然是你
Something has upset them.
它们被什么惊到了
What could it be?
怎么回事？
The weather?
可能是天气
Something in the air, perhaps?
或者空气里有什么 不确定
Best tell Joan to keep the children inside today.
告诉琼今天别让孩子们出门了
Judith?
珠迪丝？
Where are you?
你在哪儿呢？
Wake up!
醒醒啊
The baker told me her cat had kittens.
面包师的猫生小猫咪了
We need to see them.
咱们得去看看
There's eight, Judith. Eight!
有八只呢 珠迪丝 八只
We need to hurry. It's going to rain.
得抓紧了 要下雨了
Judith?
珠迪丝？
Jude?
小珠？
What's wrong?
你怎么了？
What's wrong, Judith?
哪儿不舒服？珠迪丝
Judith, answer me.
你说话啊 珠迪丝
Judith, wake up.
起来啊
Judith, please. Judith.
求你了 珠迪丝 说句话
- What is it? - It's Judith.
- 怎么了？ - 是珠迪丝
How long has she been like this?
她这样多久了？
Since I returned from school.
我从学堂回来她就这样了
Oh, my God.
天呐
She's got it.
她得上了
Hasn't she?
是不是？
She's got the pestilence.
她得了瘟疫
Hasn't she, Mama?
是不是 娘？
Go find your grandmother.
去找你奶奶
Bid her to come.
让她马上来
Now!
快去
She's burning up.
她烧得厉害
We need, um, more water.
得要水 要很多水
Make a bigger fire and heat up more water.
烧大火 把水烧热了
- We need warm water. - Eliza, fetch more water
- 需要热水 - 伊莱莎 去打些水来
and bring the Bellis from the kitchen.
把厨房的白雏菊也拿来
A row of cinnamon.
再拿肉桂
Cinnamon, that's good for drawing out the heat.
肉桂能退烧
Pineweed or a rue. Thyme, yes.
还要松草或者芸香 百里香也要
You'll find them in the room.
去屋里找
- Mama. Yeah. - The other table. The other side.
- 娘啊 - 屋里那张桌子边 桌子边
Yeah, Mama's here, my love.
娘在这儿呢 我的心肝
Here, drink this. It's rosemary and jelly.
来 喝这个 迷迭香熬的药膏
All will be well, hmm?
会没事的 听到没
All will be well.
都会没事的
Judith, stay with.
珠迪丝 坚持住
Mama's here. It's okay. Mama's here.
娘在这儿 没事的 娘在这儿
Rhubarb. We need rhubarb to purge the stomach,
大黄 得要大黄 能清肠子
drive out the pestilence.
能驱瘟疫
Can you go and fetch some?
你能去取吗？
Mama's here. It's okay. Judith, we're all here.
娘在这儿 没事的 珠迪丝 大家都在
Susanna, draw some water, too.
苏珊娜 你也去打些水来
Hamnet and... and Mary and Susanna.
哈姆奈特和玛丽还有苏珊娜
Draw water as soon as you can.
快去打水
Why isn't he here?
他怎么还没来呢？
Eliza, go write to your brother and tell him to come.
伊莱莎 去给你哥哥威廉写信 让他赶快回来
Judith.
珠迪丝
Open your mouth, Judith.
张开嘴 珠迪丝
Open your mouth. Mama's here. That's it.
张开嘴 娘在这儿 对 很好
That's good.
好孩子
Yes, you'll be safe.
对 会没事的
You'll open your mouth. Drink it down.
张开嘴 都喝下去
Swallow it down. Mama's here. It's okay, Judith.
喝下去 娘在这儿 别怕 珠迪丝
Mama's here. It's okay.
娘在这儿 别怕
Okay.
没事的
Agnes.
安妮丝
You have done all that you can.
你已经尽力了
I will not let her cross over.
我绝不会放手的
Grandmama, you had three daughters that were taken.
奶奶 你失去的三个女儿...
Were they...
也是像...
Were they like Judith?
也是像珠迪丝这样吗？
Anne was seven.
安妮那时七岁
The other two were just babies.
另两个还只是吃奶的婴儿
They all had swellings and...
都长了肿块...
【腺鼠疫: 会导致淋巴结肿大 常见于颈部 腋下和腹股沟】
...fever like Judith.
都发高烧 跟珠迪丝一样
Your mother's trying to...
你娘在...
keep a grip on her child.
拼命想保住她的孩子
It won't work.
没用的
What is given may be taken away at any time.
命是天给的 随时都能被收回
We must never let our guard down.
我们得时刻提防着
Never take for granted...
千万别把孩子们的...
...that our children's hearts beat,
每一次心跳...
that they draw breath,
每一次呼吸...
that they walk and speak and...
他们的行走 说话...
...smile, argue, play.
欢笑 吵闹和嬉戏当作理所当然的
Never forget for a moment that they may be gone.
得时刻提醒自己 他们可能说没就没了
Jude.
妹妹
小珠
Don't be sad.
别难过
You shall be well.
你要替我好好活下去
I shall not.
我不能
Not without you.
没有你我活不下去
It's here.
它来了
Do you see it, Jude?
妹妹 你看得到吗？
It's watching us.
它在看着咱们呢
I'll tell it to take us both.
我要告诉它把咱们都带走
We'll go together.
要走一起走
Turn away.
转过去
It'll make a mistake.
它会看错的
It can't tell us apart.
它分不出咱俩谁是谁
Breathe with me, Judith.
跟我一起呼吸 珠迪丝
I give you my life.
我把我的命给你
You shall be well.
你会活下去的
I give you my life, Judith.
用我的命换你的 珠迪丝
I'll be brave.
我很勇敢
I'll be brave, Father.
我是个男子汉 爹
I'll be brave.
我很勇敢
I'll be brave, Father.
我是个男子汉 爹
I'll be brave.
我是个男子汉
我很勇敢
Whoa.
驭
Quick as you can.
赶快
Hamnet.
哈姆奈特
Hamnet, you're not supposed to be down here.
醒醒 你不该在这儿睡
I need to take you up to bed.
来 我抱你上楼睡觉去...
Hamnet.
哈姆奈特
Hamnet?
哥哥？
Mama.
娘
娘啊
Hamnet.
哈姆奈特
You must open your mouth.
你得张开嘴
All will be well.
会没事的
He's burning.
他在发烧
He's burning up.
烧得太高了
It will not sti-- It will not stick!
药不起作用 不起作用
A stone. There's a stone.
拿石头 拿石头
【有洞的石头: 当时民间信仰认为病气能从一孔进 一孔出】
There's a stone upstairs with a hole in the middle of it.
楼上有块中间有洞的石头
By his bedside. Bring it down. I need it.
在他床边 快去拿来 快去
And, um, uh, salt. Get salt.
还要盐 拿盐 得撒盐
【撒盐: 当时认为能建立保护屏障 驱挡邪灵和病气】
Get it. Can you give it?
能去拿吗？
Can you f-fetch me some salt, as much salt as you have.
多拿点盐 有多少拿多少
Water. We need water.
水 还要水
He's... he's too hot.
他 他烧得太厉害了
He's burning.
太厉害了
My love. Mama's here.
我的孩子 娘在这儿
All will be well. All will be well.
坚持住 都会好的
All will be well.
都会好的
Hamnet, don't be scared.
哈姆奈特 别怕
No need to be scared.
没什么好怕的
All will be well. Mommy's here.
都会没事的 娘在这儿
Mommy's here. It's okay.
娘在 没事的
Mommy's here.
娘在这儿
Look at me. Mommy's here.
你看 娘在这儿
I will never, ever let you go.
我绝不 绝不会放手的
You understand?
明白吗？
I will never, ever let you go.
娘绝不 绝不会放手的
I love you.
娘的心肝啊
心肝啊
Eliza, take Judith to the kitchen and keep her there.
伊莱莎 把珠迪丝抱到厨房去
Please!
我不走
- He needs me! - Stay there.
- 我得陪他 - 带她走
He needs me!
我要陪我哥
Please!
我不走
Valerian...
缬草啊...
Hamnet. Hamnet. Hamnet.
哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特
Hamnet, you have to stay. Hamnet, please.
坚持住 坚持住 求你了
Hamnet, please. You have to stay with us.
哈姆奈特 求你了 你要坚持住 别离开我们
Mama needs you. We need you.
娘需要你 我们都需要你
- Stop! Enough! - Stay with us. Stay, stay.
- 住手 够了 - 别离开我们 坚持住 坚持
Please, Hamnet. Hamnet, Hamnet, Hamnet.
求求你了 哈姆奈特 坚持住 坚持住
- Let him alone! - Hamnet, please!
- 别折腾他了 - 求求你了 哈姆奈特
Can't you see that it's too late for him!
你看不出来吗 太晚了
Please, please.
求你了 求你了
Hamnet?
哈姆奈特？
Hamnet. Hamnet. Please. Hamnet.
哈姆奈特 哈姆奈特 求你了 哈姆奈特
My son is gone.
我儿子没了
Just so bereft... it's my son.
没了 我的儿子
I've lost my...
没了 我...
I saw the light, and I couldn't sleep.
我看灯还亮着 我也睡不着
Here.
来
Oh, child, no.
哎呀 孩子 不行
- No, no, no. Go to bed. - No, no, let-let her stay.
- 不 快去睡觉 - 没事 没事 让她看吧
It is my fault, Mama. It is my fault.
是我害的 娘 都是我害的
No. No.
不 不
It is not your fault, Judith.
珠迪丝 这不是你的错
But he changed places with me.
他替了我
He tricked it.
他骗了它
He tricked what?
他骗了什么？
Death.
死神
Judith.
珠迪丝
It took him when it came for me.
它来找我时 却把他夺走了
Never say those words to anyone ever again.
这话绝对不许再说
The fever came for your brother, and it took him.
你哥是因为发烧走的
Do you wish to see him?
你想看看他吗？
Yes.
想
Go on. You can see him.
去吧 去看看他
Is it really him?
这真的是他吗？
Yes.
是的
It-it doesn't look like him.
这 这不像我哥
No.
不
It's not him.
这不是他
It's not.
不是
It's not him.
这不是我哥
It-It's-it's not morning yet.
天 天还没亮呢
We haven't prepared him properly.
还没给他收拾好呢
Am I too late?
我来晚了吗？
- It's you. - Father.
- 是你 - 爹
It's you.
真的是你
It's me.
真是我
Where is he?
儿子呢？
Where is...
他在哪儿...
Where...
他在...
It's my boy.
是我儿子
是我的儿子啊
I didn't see it.
我没预见到
I should've paid him more attention.
我该多留心哈姆奈特的
I always thought she was the one to be taken away
我一直以为会失去珠迪丝
when all the while it was him.
没想到是儿子
I'm a fool.
我太蠢了
No, there's nothing anyone could have done to save him.
不是 没人能救他
You did everything that you could.
你已经尽力了
Of course I did.
我是尽力了
You weren't here.
可你人呢？
I would have cut my heart out and given it to him.
我愿把心掏给他
I would have laid my life down on the ground for him.
用我的命换他的命
- I-I know. I know. - And no one would take it.
- 我懂 我懂 - 可上天不收
- But you... - No, you don't know.
- 可你... - 不 你不懂
You don't know. You weren't here.
你怎么可能懂 你都不在啊
He died in agony.
他在折磨中死去
I...
我...
- He was in agony. - Agnes.
- 受尽了折磨 - 安妮丝
He cried and he cried
他哭个不停 他哭啊 哭啊
- and he cried and he cried. - Agnes, stop, stop.
-  哭啊 哭啊 哭啊 - 安妮丝 别这样
- And his little body was wracked in pain. - Shh.
- 他小小的身子在剧痛中抽搐 - 嘘
No, don't shush me.
不 别让我闭嘴
He was so scared.
他当时好害怕
- And you weren't here. - I know.
- 你却没在身边 - 我知道
I tried everything I could.
我什么办法都用了
I know you did.
我知道你做了
- I tried everything I could. - You did everything that you could.
- 我什么都试过了 - 你已经尽了一切
You did everything that you could.
你已经用尽了一切办法
Everything.
一切办法
Agnes. Agnes.
安妮丝 安妮丝
I will send word, Agnes.
我会捎信的 安妮丝
You'll send word?
捎信？
- To whom? - To you.
- 捎给谁啊？ - 给你啊
I'm here.
我就在这儿啊
What I meant was that I shall send word when I reach London.
我是说到了伦敦我会给你捎信的
London?
伦敦？
I must leave.
我得走了
Leave? How can you leave?
走？你怎么能走？
The world does simply not stand still, Agnes.
世界不会因为我们就停下来 安妮丝
There are people waiting for me in London.
伦敦还有人在等我
The season is about to begin,
演出季马上就要开始了
and my company shall return from Kent any day now.
我们的剧团随时都会从肯特郡回来
I have to go now.
我现在就得走了
Now?
现在？
There's a traveling party leaving today,
今天有个商队要出发
and they have a spare horse, so yeah.
他们有匹多余的马 现在就得走
Look after the girls, and I will return to--
照看好女儿们 我回来时会...
Stop.
住手
Don't.
别碰我
Go. Go.
走吧 你走吧
（哈姆奈特）
"When I do count the clock that tells the time,
“蒙晨暮鼓催岁长”
"And see the brave day sunk in hideous night;
“夕太沉沉入幽光”
"When I behold the violet past prime,
“芳草奇花香自散”
"And sable curls all silver'd o'er with white;
“青丝墨字今已霜”
"When lofty trees I see barren of leaves
“繁荫不复幕沧桑”
"Which erst from the heat did canopy the herd,
“牧群归舍众组忙”
"And summer's green all girded up in sheaves
“夏末青禾束成囊”
"Borne on the bier with white and bristly beard;
“犹似亡魂缠白裳”
"Then of thy beauty do I question make,
“容颜岂非浮云妆”
"Thou among the wastes of time must go,
“终将消散入苍茫”
"Since sweets and beauties do themselves forsake
“芬芳娇艳随风扬”
"And die as fast as they see others grow;
“新生如笋催人苍”
"And nothing gainst time's scythe can make defense
“时光镰刀谁能挡”
Save breed, to brave him when he takes thee hence."
“勇敢生育续春阳”
【十四行诗: 现代编号第12首 以时间流逝与生育为主题】
Will you read it again?
能再读一遍吗？
No.
不了
I've read it three times.
我已经读了三遍了
That's enough.
行了
- Shall we do presents? - Presents? from London?
- 咱们开始拆礼物吧 - 什么礼物？伦敦的吗？
A hair comb for you, Jude.
给你的梳子 小珠
Mind you, you'll have to be careful.
爱惜点用 别弄坏了
This is for you, Agnes.
这是给你的 安妮丝
- A ruby, is it? - Mm-hmm.
- 红宝石吗？ - 是的
It's the finest I've ever seen.
从没见过这么漂亮的
Everyone's talking about the new house.
大家都在议论那栋新房子
It's the biggest in Stratford.
那是斯特拉特福镇上最大的房子
There are so many rooms. One could get lost.
房间多到人进去都能走丢
You shall keep the keys, Susanna.
苏珊娜 那就好好照看好
You shall manage the house well.
打理好咱们的房子
Put it on, Mama.
娘 你戴上试试
Did Bartholomew show you the new house?
你哥巴塞洛缪带你看过那栋房子了吗？
Mm-hmm.
看了
Do you like it?
你喜欢吗？
Why didn't you show me yourself?
你怎么不亲自带我去看的？
Were you afraid I wouldn't leave?
是怕我不愿离开吗？
'Cause Hamnet died here in this house.
因为哈姆奈特死在这个房子里
You know, I'm constantly wondering where he is.
我一直在想他在哪儿？
Or where he has gone.
他去了哪儿？
Whatever I'm doing, I'm wondering, "Where is he?"
不管我做什么 脑子里都是他在哪儿？
I mean, he can't have just vanished.
他不能就这么凭空没了啊
All he needs is for me to find him.
我一定要找到他
He must be somewhere.
他肯定在哪个地方
I fear I may run mad with it, even now, a year on.
都一年了还是这样 我真害怕自己会疯掉
A year is nothing.
一年算什么啊
A year is nothing. It's every second...
一年什么都不是 每时每刻...
every minute, every day.
每分每秒 每天每年
We may never stop looking for him.
我们怎么可能停止寻找啊
I'm sorry, Agnes.
对不起 安妮丝
Did you hear me? I said that I'm sorry, Agnes.
听到了吗？我说对不起 安妮丝
- For what? - For everything.
- 为什么道歉？ - 为这一切
- You're caught by that place. - For...
- 你被那地方缠住了 - 为...
- What place? - That place in your head.
- 什么地方？ - 你脑子里那个地方
It is now more real to you than anywhere else.
对你来说 那地方比什么都好
Not even the death of our child can keep you from it.
连咱儿子死了都留不住你
Hamnet died.
哈姆奈特死了
A horrible death.
死得很惨
And you should have been there.
你本该在场
You could have bid him farewell.
你本可跟他道个别
What do you see?
你看到了什么？
Hmm?
什么？
Nothing.
什么都没有
Nothing?
什么都没有？
Nothing at all.
什么都没有
Oh, well.
好吧
You should go back to London.
你还是回伦敦吧
You need not concern yourself with us.
不用为我们操心
Get along just fine without you.
没有你我们的日子也照过
This was sometime a paradox,
“这句话从前是个似是而非的悖论”
but now the time gives it proof.
“如今已被时间所证实”
I did love you once.
“我确实曾爱过你”
Indeed, my lord, you made me believe so.
“没错 殿下 您确实让我信以为真”
You should not have believed me,
“你当初就不该相信我”
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock for...
“美德嫁接到我们这罪恶的老树干上 也...”
You should not have believed me,
“你当初就不该相信我”
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock
“美德嫁接到我们这罪恶的老树干上”
but we shall relish of it.
“也结不出好果”
I loved you not.
“我从未真爱过你”
I was the more deceived.
“那我真是被深深欺骗了”
Get thee to a nunnery.
“去美人庵吧”
【美人庵: 指女性宗教修行场所 又为妓院俚语 此处含贬低之意】
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
“干嘛非得生出一堆罪人来？”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“我自己还算个老实人”
but yet I could accuse me of such things
“但我的罪过却多得数不清”
that it were better to...
“最大的莫过于...”
Again.
重来
Get thee to a nunnery.
“去美人庵吧”
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
“干嘛非得生出一堆罪人来？”
I am myself indifferent honest, but...
“我自己也算个老实人 但...”
Again. "I am myself indifferent honest." Again.
重来 是“我自己还算个老实人” 重来
I am myself indifferent honest,
“我自己还算个老实人”
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were better
“但我的罪过却多得数不清 最大的莫过于”
- my mother had not borne me. - Again.
- “我娘把我生了出来” - 重来
I, myself...
“我这个人...”
- And... - Again.
- 呃... - 再来
I, myself, am indifferent...
“我这个人...自己还算个...”
"I am myself."
是“我自己”
I am myself indifferent honest,
“我自己还算个老实人”
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
“但我的罪过却多得数不清...”
Again.
再来
But yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
“但我的罪过却多得数不清...”
Again!
重来
I am myself indifferent honest,
“我自己还算个老实人”
but yet I could accuse me of such...
“但我的罪过...”
You are simply mouthing the words!
你根本没投入
I am myself indifferent honest,
我自己还算个老实人
but yet I could accuse me of such things
但我的罪过却多得数不清
that it were better my mother had not borne me.
最大的莫过于我娘把我生了出来
I am very proud, revengeful, ambitious,
我这人自傲 报复心强 野心大
with more offenses at my beck
肚子里装的那些坏主意
than I have thoughts to put them in,
多到我都数不清
imagination to give them shape or time to act them in.
想都想不尽 干也干不完
Now, what should such fellows as I do
像我这样的人
crawling between heaven and earth?
在天地之间苟活 有什么用？
We are arrant knaves all.
我们全是烂透的坏人
Believe none of us.
你可千万不要信我们
Go thy ways to a nunnery. Again.
去你的美人庵吧 重来
To be...
生存...
...or not to be...
还是毁灭...
...that is the question:
这是个问题
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to... suffer
哪种更高贵？是默然 忍受...
The slings and arrows of...
命运投来的巨石...
...outrageous fortune...
射来的毒箭？
...Or...
还是...
...to take arms against a...
挺身反抗...
...sea of troubles,
汹涌的苦海...
And by opposing...
通过斗争...
...end them.
渡向彼岸？
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ For ♪
♪ 只因... ♪
♪ Sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
【《我那去了绿林的知更鸟》: 英国民谣 绿林象征身后世界 知更鸟象征逝者】
Agnes?
安妮丝？
I... I was in town, and I...
我 我碰巧来镇上
I thought I would pay you a visit.
就想顺路来看下你
I was very sorry to hear about John's passing.
听说你公公约翰去世了 替你们难过
How's your husband?
你丈夫还好吧
It's a... it's a terrible thing to lose one's father.
失去父亲 真是件悲痛的事啊
He's well.
他好得很
He's very busy. He's preparing a comedy.
忙得要命 还在搞一出喜剧
His new play is not a comedy.
他的新剧可不是喜剧
It's a tragedy.
是悲剧
But you knew that.
你应该早知道了
Everyone in town is talking about it.
镇上人人都在谈论
I did warn you about marrying him...
我是劝过你别嫁给他...
Don't pretend that you care for me.
别装作疼我
You are not my mother, and you never were.
你不是我娘 永远也不是
Good day, Agnes.
再见 安妮丝
He's not spoken to us for months.
他都好几个月没跟我们联系了
How could he...
他怎么能
How could he not tell us?
他怎么能不告诉我们呢？
Do you not wonder what is in it?
你不想看看吗？
In what?
看什么？
（《哈姆雷特的悲剧》）
The play.
这剧
Who are you looking for?
你们找谁呢？
William Shakespeare.
威廉·莎士比亚
We're his family from Stratford.
我们是他的家人 从斯特拉特福来的
Go up the stairs. He lives in the attic.
上楼 他住阁楼
Why would the man with the largest house in Stratford
拥有斯特拉特福最大房子的人
be living here?
怎么会住在这样的地方？
I don't understand.
我不明白
I thought...
我以为...
I thought he...
我以为他...
What shall I do?
我该怎么办？
Keep your heart open.
敞开心扉
（天下皆为舞台）
【拉丁格言"天下皆为舞台 人人都是演员" 莎士比亚《皆大欢喜》亦用此意象】
【译注: 当时剧场分为站票 看台 包厢等级】
（《哈姆奈特的悲剧》）
- Who's there? - Nay, answer me:
- 谁呀？ - 不 先回答我
stand and unfold yourself!
出来 报上名来
Long live the king!
国王万岁
【国王万岁: 执勤人员碰头暗号】
Bernardo?
伯纳多？
If you do meet Horatio and Marcellus,
要是碰到我的夜班同伴
The rivals to my watch, bid them make haste.
霍拉旭和马塞拉斯 叫他们速来
I think I hear them. Stand, ho!
他们好像来了 站住 谁
Who's there?
是谁？
Has this thing appeared again tonight?
它今晚又现身了吗？
- I have seen nothing. - Horatio says...
- 我还没看见 - 霍拉旭说...
What are they talking about?
这演的什么啊
...'tis but our fantasy...
这不过是我们的幻觉
...and will not let belief take hold of him touching...
我曾和他说过 他就是不信...
What has any of this to do with my son?
这和我儿子有什么关系？
...this dreaded sight twice seen of us...
我们已经见过两次这可怕的景象...
These men are frightened.
他们很害怕
Of what?
有什么好怕的
And let us once again assail your ears...
别不信 让我们再给你解释一遍...
They watch for a ghost.
他们在提防一个幽灵
...when yond same star that's westward from the pole...
昨天这个时候 北极星西侧的星到这个位置时...
Ghost?
幽灵？
...The bell then beating one...
钟刚好敲了一下...
Peace; break thee off!
快住嘴 别说了
Look where it comes again!
看 它又现身了
In the same figure, like the king that's dead.
一模一样 就像那位已故的先王
See, it stalks away!
看 它阔步离去了
That was him.
那是他
...Tell me why this same...
谁能告诉我 为什么...
- That was Will. - Shh.
- 那是威廉 - 嘘
- He's not in the play. - No, no.
- 他不是演员 - 不 不
It was Will as a ghost.
那幽灵就是威廉演的
Our last king, Whose image but now appeared to us,
刚才向我们显灵的那位先王
Was dared to the combat; our valiant Hamlet...
正是那场决斗中 英勇的哈姆雷特国王...
Hamlet.
哈姆雷特
Did you hear... did you hear that?
你听到了 你听到了吗？
Yes.
听到了
They said his-- they said his name.
他们念了 念了他的名字
Agnes.
安妮丝
- Agnes, wait. - Out of my way!
- 安妮丝 别 - 让开
Please be quiet.
安静
Wait, did they say his name? Huh?
他们干嘛念他的名字啊
Do not upset yourself.
别自找苦吃
Why is-- Why did he use his name?
他凭什么 凭什么喊我儿子的名字？
- I don't know him. - Quiet.
- 他当他谁啊 - 安静
...and by my advice,
...依我之见
Let us impart what we have seen tonight
不如将我们今晚所见
Unto the young prince...
禀告给年轻的王子...
Don't you dare pronounce my son's name!
不许念我儿子的名字
Quiet!
闭嘴
...dumb to us, will speak to him.
...对我们沉默的幽灵 会对他说话
Though yet of our dear brother's death,
虽说大家对我亲爱的王兄死讯
The memory be green,
还记忆犹新
Yet so far hath discretion fought with nature
但我们要节哀顺变
That we with wisest sorrow think on him,
在深切缅怀他的同时
Together with remembrance of ourselves.
也要为我们自身着想啊
I will not stay a minute longer to be a part of this jest.
我受不了 我不能再看下去了
- Wait. One moment. - ...my cousin.
- 别急 再看一会儿 - 我的侄儿
- No. I want to go home. -  Hamlet...
- 不 我要回家 - 哈姆雷特
【哈姆雷特: 原著中先王与王子同名皆为哈姆雷特】
and my son...
现在也是我的儿子
How is it that the clouds still hang on you?
你怎么还一脸愁云？
Good Hamlet, cast thy nighted color off.
我的好哈姆雷特 脱去这沉重的黑衣
Do not for ever with thy vailed lids
别总是低眉垂眼的
Seek for thy noble father in the dust.
仿佛要从尘土中寻出你高贵的父亲
All that lives must die,
万物有生必有死
Passing through nature to eternity.
顺其自然 谁都会踏入永恒
Ay, madam, it is common.
是啊 母后 这确实是常理
But I have that within which passes show.
但我心中的郁结
These are but the trappings and the suits of woe.
远非这些丧服哀装所能表达
To persevere In obstinate condolement
固执地沉溺于哀伤
is a course of impious stubbornness.
是一种逆天的愚行
'Tis unmanly grief.
这不是堂堂男子的悲伤
It shows a will most incorrect to heaven.
是对天意的违抗
Oh.
哦
This too, too solid flesh would melt,
真想这 这沉重的肉体消融
Thaw and resolve itself into a dew.
化为晨露消散
Or that the Everlasting had not fixed
真想永恒的真神
His canon gainst self-slaughter.
未曾禁止自杀这罪孽
'Tis an unweeded garden That grows to seed;
这就是一座荒芜不治 杂草丛生
things rank and gross in nature possess it merely.
长满毒花恶草的花园
That it should come to this.
谁曾料到啊
But two months dead--
才死了两个月
nay, not so much, not two--
不 还没满两个月
So excellent a king, that was to this
那是一位多么杰出的国王 如同太阳神
Hyperion to a... a satyr.
而现在这位 却像只肮脏的禽兽
Whither wilt thou lead me?
你要领我上哪儿去？
Speak. I'll go no further.
快说 我不跟你走
I am thy father's spirit,
我是你父亲的灵魂
Doomed for a certain term to walk the night,
被判在夜间游走于这大地
And for the day confined to fast in fires.
白天则要忍受地狱烈火的焚烧
My hour is almost come
我的时辰快到了
When I to sulfurous and tormenting flames
我又得回到硫磺的火焰中...
Must render up myself.
去遭受痛苦的煎熬
- Alas, poor ghost. - No, pity me not...
- 唉 可怜的幽灵 - 不 不要可怜我...
...but lend thy serious hearing to what I shall unfold.
你只要留心听着我要告诉你的话
List.
听好
List, oh, list.
听好 啊 听好了
If thou didst ever thy father love...
要是你曾深爱过你的父亲
Oh, God.
天呐
But soft, methinks I scent the morning air.
且慢 我仿佛闻到了清晨的气息
Brief let me be. Sleeping within my orchard.
我长话短说 那天我照常在花园里午睡
Upon my secure hour, thy uncle stole
你叔父趁我熟睡之际偷溜进来
With juice of cursed hebona in a vile,
拿着一瓶天杀的剧毒毒液
Within the porches of my ears did pour
灌入了我的耳朵
The leprous distillment...
这麻风病般的毒液...
...whose effect Holds such an enmity with blood of man
毒性之大 嗜血如仇
That swift as quicksilver it courses through
它顺着血管流动得比水银还快
The natural gates and alleys of the body.
流遍全身七窍八脉
And with a sudden vigor it doth posset
突然一下子
And curd, like...
就凝固了我的血...
...eager droppings into milk,
像卤水点豆腐一样
The thin and wholesome blood.
把我健康的血液彻底摧毁了
So did it mine.
我就这样被毒害了
A most instant tetter barked about...
转眼间我全身长满了烂疮...
...Most lazar-like, with vile and loathsome crust,
如癞病般浑身长满可憎的痂皮
All my smooth body.
体无完肤
Oh.
啊
Horrible.
惨呀
Oh, horrible. Most horrible.
哦 惨啊 太惨了
If thou hast nature in thee, bear it not...
只要你还有人性 就不要再忍了...
He has swapped places with our son.
他成了我们的儿子
Look at me.
回头看我
The... the glowworm shows the matin to be near,
萤 萤火虫的微光已经暗淡
And 'gins to pale his uneffectual fires.
黎明就要来了
My boy.
我的儿子啊
Adieu.
再会了
Remember me.
记着我
To be, or not to be,
生存还是毁灭
that is the question.
这是个问题
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to suffer
哪种更高贵？是默然忍受
The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
命运投来的巨石 射来的毒箭？
Or to take arms against a sea of troubles
还是挺身反抗汹涌的苦海
And, by opposing, end them.
通过斗争 渡向彼岸？
To die, to sleep,
死了 沉睡了
No more.
就那样了
And by a sleep, to say we end
要是一场睡眠可以终结
The heartache and the thousand natural shocks
我们这些血肉之躯生来要承受的
That flesh is heir to-- 'tis a consummation
万千苦难 那可是天大的好事
Devoutly to be wished.
是求之不得的结局
To die,
死了
To sleep, perchance to dream.
沉睡了 没准还有梦呢
Ay, there's the rub.
啊 这就是问题
For in that sleep of death, what dreams may come
摆脱了这凡尘肉体 在那死亡的沉睡中
When we have shuffled off this mortal coil
我们会做什么梦
Must give us pause.
这必然令人踌躇
There's the respect
正是这份顾虑
That makes calamity of so long life.
让我们心甘陷入这漫长的苦难
Who would bear the whips and scorns of time,
谁甘心忍受这人世的鞭挞和嘲辱
The oppressor's wrong,
压迫的屈辱
the proud man's contumely,
傲慢的蔑辱
The pangs of despised love,
心碎的羞辱
the law's delay,
法律的冷辱
The insolence of office, and the spurns
官吏的欺辱 以及小人对
That patient merit of the unworthy take,
勤勤恳恳老实人的侮辱
When he himself might his quietus make
否则当一把匕首就能解脱
With a bare bodkin?
谁不愿意？
Who would fardels bear,
谁愿背负这重担
To grunt and sweat under a weary life,
撑着这疲惫的身躯呻吟 流汗
But that the dread of something after death,
要不是死后那无人归返
The undiscovered country from whose bourn
未知的国度令我们恐惧
No traveler returns, puzzles the will,
困扰了我们的意志
And makes us rather bear those ills...
使我们宁愿忍受眼前的不幸...
En garde!
各就各位
One!
一剑
No! No!
不 没有击中
A hit, a palpable hit!
中了 很明显的一剑
Our son shall win!
我们的儿子一定会胜利
- Well, again! - Gertrude, do not drink.
- 好吧 再来 - 格特鲁德 别喝
Another hit! What say you?
又是一剑 你自己说中没中
Have at you now!
吃我一剑
How does the queen?
王后怎么了？
She swoons to see them bleed.
她肯定是晕血了
No, no, the drink, the drink!
不 不 是那酒 那酒
Oh, my dear Hamlet.
啊 我心爱的哈姆雷特
I am poisoned.
我中毒了
Oh, villainy!
啊 恶毒的阴谋
Ho, let the door be locked!
喂 把门锁上
Treachery! Seek it out!
奸贼 揪出来
It is here, Hamlet.
哈姆雷特 奸贼就在这儿
Hamlet, thou art slain.
哈姆雷特 你也要死了
No medicine in the world can do thee good.
没有药能救得了你
In thee, there is not half an hour's life.
你活不到半个钟头了
The king's to blame!
都是国王做的孽
The point envenomed, too?
剑头也有毒药？
Then, venom, to thy work!
那么好 毒药 也给你
Here, thou incestuous, murderous, damned Dane!
你这个乱伦的 血腥的丹麦的魔王
Drink...
给我喝...
Drink off this potion!
喝下这杯毒酒
Is thy union here?
你那心爱的珍珠在里面吗？
【心爱的珍珠: 具双关 既指原著中的珍珠 又指婚姻】
Follow my mother.
跟我的母亲一道去吧
I am dead.
我死了
Thou livest.
可你还活着
Report me and my cause aright
请将我的故事与大义
To the unsatisfied.
如实告知尚不知情的人吧
If thou didst ever hold me in thy heart,
若你曾对我怀有深情与敬重
Absent thee from felicity awhile,
暂且别去享那极乐
And in this harsh world draw thy breath in pain
留在这残酷的尘世 隐忍着痛苦
To tell my story.
去把我的故事讲清
Ah, I die!
啊 我要死了
The potent poison quite o'ercrows my spirit.
这剧毒正夺去我的意志
The rest is silence.
余下的只有沉寂
导演
赵婷
编剧
玛姬·欧法洛
改编
自玛姬·欧法洛同名小说
《哈姆内特》
制片人
丽莎·马歇尔
皮帕·哈里斯
尼古拉斯·贡达
制片人
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
萨姆·门德斯
执行制片人
克里斯蒂·麦克斯科·克里格
赵婷
劳里·博格
联合制片人
玛姬·欧法洛
卡罗琳·雷诺兹
摄影指导
乌卡什·扎尔
艺术指导
菲奥娜·克隆比
剪辑
赵婷
阿方索·贡萨尔维斯
服装设计
马尔戈西亚·图尔赞斯卡
音效
约翰尼·伯恩
配乐
马克斯·李希特
选角指导
妮娜·戈尔德
主演
杰西·巴克利 饰 莎士比亚妻子安妮丝
保罗·麦斯卡 饰 安妮丝丈夫威廉·莎士比亚
主演
艾米丽·沃森 饰 莎士比亚母亲玛丽
乔·阿尔文 饰 安妮丝哥哥巴塞洛缪
主演
雅各比·朱佩 饰 儿子哈姆奈特
奥利维娅·莱恩斯 饰 小女儿珠迪丝
主演
贾斯汀·米切尔 饰 安妮丝继母琼
大卫·威尔莫特 饰 莎士比亚父亲约翰
主演
路易莎·哈兰德 饰 安妮丝生母罗文
弗蕾亚·汉南-米尔斯 饰 莎士比亚妹妹伊莱莎
波德希·雷·布雷斯纳赫 饰 大女儿苏珊娜
主演
诺亚·尤佩 饰 《哈姆雷特的悲剧》戏中哈姆雷特王子
赵婷
导演作品
字幕译制
蒙太奇字幕组
字幕贡献者
翻译/校对/时间轴/后期：小p
后期/时间轴：NickCollect
特别感谢
朱生豪, 卞之琳, 梁实秋
傅光明, 党晟, 孙大雨 等翻译家
莎士比亚学家：Stephen Greenblatt
语言学家：Joseph S. Hopkins
多个在线研究项目
以及《哈姆奈特》电影和小说的所有参与者
本故事是对莎士比亚文学遗产的多层致敬。
草药意象直接呼应《哈姆雷特》中欧菲莉亚的悲剧台词；
男孩女孩的换装设定则致敬了
《威尼斯商人》《皆大欢喜》和《第十二夜》中的经典桥段；
而安妮丝列出的多个意象
（空间、洞穴、悬崖、隧道、大海、虚空与未知国度）
亦呼应了莎翁多部作品中常见的主题。
鉴于娱乐性与学术性的平衡考量，
本作翻译以剧情呈现为主，
尊重导演的创意表达，
对莎翁文学深层意义的阐释有限，敬请理解。
@MontageSubs
欢迎加入我们的 Telegram / IRC 社群深入交流讨论
蒙太奇字幕组
字幕许可 CC BY-NC-SA 4.0
♪ My Robin to the greenwood will go ♪
♪ 我的知更鸟啊 飞向了那绿林 ♪
♪ Where the oak and the ash ♪
♪ 那里有橡树也有白蜡 ♪
♪ And the briars do grow ♪
♪ 还有那尖刺的荆棘 ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 爱人啊 你可好啊 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 夜幕吞噬了森林 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 深陷那幽闭的树影里 ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ 你可好啊 ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 爱人啊 你可好啊 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 夜幕吞噬了森林 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 深陷那幽闭的树影里 ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ 你可好啊 ♪
♪ The greenwood is near ♪
♪ 绿林啊 近在咫尺 ♪
♪ And the greenwood is far ♪
♪ 绿林啊 又远在天边 ♪
♪ And many a danger ♪
♪ 无数的危险啊 ♪
♪ Befalls a man there ♪
♪ 潜伏在那里 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 只因那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ Is all my joy ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我祈求那些树啊 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 还我男孩来 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 只因那只温柔的知更鸟 ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
♪ 是我仅有的幸福 ♪
（焦点影业）
蒙太奇字幕组 (MontageSubs)
用爱发电 ♥ Powered by Love